Fire and water.
Now, if you wish, like the dorbs, to hear news of Smile, you must go back
again to the evening when he smashed the door and flew off in rage two days
before. The men of the Lake Town Esgaroth were mostly indoors, for the
breeze was from the black east and chill, but a few were walking on the
keys and watching, as they were fond of doing, the stars shine out from the
smooth patches of the lake as they opened in the sky. From their town the
lonely mountain was mostly screened by the low hills at the far end of the lake
through a gap in which the running river came down from the north. Only its high
peak could they see in clear weather, and they looked seldom at it, for it was
ominous and dreer even in the light of morning. Now it was lost and gone,
blotted in the dark. Suddenly it flickered back to view. A brief glow
touched it and faded. Look, said one, the lights again. Last night the
watchman saw them start and fade from midnight until dawn. Something is
happening up there. Perhaps the king under the mountain is forging gold, said
another. It is long since he went north.
It is time the songs began to prove themselves again. Which king? said
another with a grim voice. as like as not. It is the marauding fire of the
dragon, the only king under the mountain we have ever known.
You are always forboding gloomy things, said the others. Anything from floods to
poisoned fish. Think of something cheerful.
Then suddenly a great light appeared in the low place in the hills and the
northern end of the lake turned golden.
The king beneath the mountain. they shouted. His wealth is like the sun, his
silver like a fountain. His river's golden run. The river is running gold
from the mountain. They cried, and everywhere windows were opening and feet
were hurrying. There was once more a tremendous excitement and enthusiasm,
but the grimvoiced fellow ran hot to the master. "The dragon is coming, or I am a
fool," he cried. "Cut the bridges to arms! to arms. Then warning trumpets
were suddenly sounded and echoed along the rocky shores. The cheering stopped,
and the joy was turned to dread.
So it was that the dragon did not find them quite unprepared.
Before long, so great was his speed.
They could see him as a spark of fire rushing towards them, and growing ever
huger and more bright. and not the most foolish doubted that the prophecies had
gone rather wrong. Still they had a little time. Every vessel in the town
was filled with water. Every warrior was armed. Every arrow and dart was ready.
And the bridge to the land was thrown down and destroyed before the roar of
Smow's terrible approach grew loud, and the lake rippled red as fire beneath the
awful beating of his wings. amid shrieks and wailing and the shouts of many came
over them, swept towards the bridges and was foiled. The bridge was gone, and his
enemies were on an island in deep water too deep and dark and cool for his
liking. If he plunged into it, a vapor in a steam would arise enough to cover
all the land with a mist for days, but the lake was mightier than he, it would
quench him before he could pass through.
Roaring, he swept back over the town. A hail of dark arrows leaped up and
snapped and rattled on his scales and jewels, and their shafts fell back,
kindled by his breath, burning and hissing into the lake. No fireworks you
ever imagined equaled the sights that night. At the twanging of the bows and
the shrilling of the trumpets, the dragon's wrath blazed to its height,
till he was blind and mad with it. No one had dared to give battle to him for
many in age, nor would they have dared now if it had not been for the
grimvoiced man. Bard was his name, who ran to and fro, cheering on the archers
and urging the master to order them to fight to the last arrow. Fire leaped
from the dragon's jaws. He settled for a while high in the air above them,
lighting all the lake. The trees by the shore shone like copper and like blood
with leaping shadows of dense black at their feet. Then down he swooped
straight through the arrowstorm, reckless in his rage, taking no heed to
turn his scaly sides towards his foes, seeking only to set their town ablaze.
Fire leaped from thatched roofs and wooden beammens as he hurdled down and
passed and round again, though all had been drenched with water before he came.
Once more water was flung by a hundred hands wherever a spark appeared.
Back swirled the dragon.
A sweep of his tail and the roof of the great house crumbled and smashed down.
Flames unquenchable sprang high into the night. Another swoop and another and
another [clears throat] house and then another sprang a fire and fell and still
no arrow hindered Smal or hurt him more than a fly from the marshes. Already men
were jumping into the water on every side. Women and children were being
huddled into laden boats in the market pool. Weapons were flung down. There was
mourning and weeping where but a little time ago the old songs of mirth to come
had been sung about the dwarves. Now men cursed their names. The master himself
was turning to his great gilded boat, hoping to row away in the confusion and
save himself. Soon all the town would be deserted and burned down to the surface
of the lake. That was the dragon's hope.
They could all get into boats for all he cared. There he could have fine sport
hunting them, or they could stop till they starved. Let them try to get to
land, and he would be ready. Soon he would set all the shoreland woods ablaze
and wither every field and pasture. Just now he was enjoying the sport of town
baiting more than he had enjoyed anything for years. But there was still
a company of archers that held their ground among the burning houses. Their
captain was barred, grimvoiced and grim-faced, whose friends had accused
him of prophesying floods and poisoned fish, though they knew his worth and
courage. He was a descendant in long line of Jiren, lord of Dale, whose wife
and child had escaped down the running river from the ruin long ago. Now he
shot with a great yubo to all his arrows but one were spent. The flames were near
him. His companions were leaving him. He bent his bow for the last time.
Suddenly, out of the dark, something fluttered to his shoulder. He started,
but it was only an old thrush. Unafraid, it perched by his ear, and it brought
him news. Marveling, he found he could understand its tongue, for he was of the
race of Dale. "Wait, wait," it said to him. "The moon is rising. Look for the
hollow of the left breast as he flies and turns above you." And while Bard
paused in wonder, it told him of tidings up in the mountain, and of all that it
had heard. Then Bard drew his bow string to his ear. The dragon was circling
back, flying low, and as he came, the moon rose above the eastern shore and
silvered his great wings. "Arow," said the bowman. "Black Arrow, I have saved
you to the last. You have never failed me, and always I have recovered you. I
had you from my father, and he from of old. If ever you came from the forges of
the true king under the mountain, go now and speed well. The dragon swooped once
more lower than ever, and as he turned and dived down his belly, glittered
white with sparkling fires of gems in the moon, but not in one place. The
great bow twanged. The black arrow sped straight from the string, straight for
the hollow by the left breast, where the forleg was flung wide. In its smoke and
vanished barb, shaft and feather, so fierce was its flight. With a shriek
that deafened men, felled trees and split stone, smugg shot spouting into
the air, turned over and crashed down from on high in ruin. Full on the town
he fell. His last throws splintered it to sparks and gleeds. The lake roared
in. A vast steam leaped up white in the sudden dark under the moon. There was a
hiss, a gushing whirl, and then silence, and that was the end of Smog and
Esgarov, but not of Bard. The waxing moon rose higher and higher, and the
wind grew loud and cold. It twisted the white fog into bending pillars and
hurrying clouds, and drove it off to the west to scatter and tattered shreds over
the marshes before Murkwood. Then the many boats could be seen dotted dark on
the surface of the lake, and down the wind came the voices of the people of
Esgaroth lamenting their lost town and goods and ruined houses. But they had
really much to be thankful for, had they thought of it, though it could hardly be
expected that they should just then 34 of the people of the town had at least
escaped alive. their woods and fields and pastures and cattle and most of
their boats remained undamaged, and the dragon was dead. What that meant they
had not yet realized.
They gathered in mournful crowds upon the western shores, shivering in the
cold wind, and their first complaints and anger were against the master, who
had left the town so soon, while some were still willing to defend it. He may
have a good head for business, especially his own business. some
murmured. But he is no good when anything serious happens. And they
praised the courage of Bard and his last mighty shot. If only he had not been
killed, they all said, "We would make him a king." Bard the dragon shooter of
the line of Jiren. Alas that he is lost.
And in the very midst of their talk, a tall figure stepped from the shadows. He
was drenched with water. His black hair hung wet over his face and shoulders,
and a fierce light was in his eyes.
"Bard is not lost," he cried. He dived from Ezra when the enemy was slain. "I
am Bard of the light of Jiren. I am the slayer of the dragon." "King Bard, King
Bard," they shouted. But the master ground his chattering teeth. Jiren was
Lord of Dale, not King of Asgaroth. He said, "In the Lake Town, we have always
elected masters from among the old and wise, and have not endured the rule of
mere fighting men. Let King Bard go back to his own kingdom." Dale is now freed
by his valor, and nothing hinders his return. And any that wish can go with
him, if they prefer the cold stones under the shadow of the mountain to the
green shores of the lake. The wise will stay here and hope to rebuild our town
and enjoy again in time its peace and riches.
We will have King Bard. The people near at hand shouted in reply. We have had
enough of the old men and the money counters and people further off took up
the cry up the Bowman and down with moneybags till the clamor echoed along
the shore. I am the last man to undervalue Bard the Bowman, said the
master wearily, for Bard now stood close beside him. He has tonight earned an
eminent place in the role of the benefactors of our town, and he is
worthy of many imperishable songs. But why, oh people, and here the master rose
to his feet and spoke very loud and clear, why do I get all your blame?
For what fault am I to be deposed? Who aroused the dragon from his slumber? I
might ask, who obtained of us rich gifts and ample help, and led us to believe
that old songs could come true? Who played on our soft hearts and our
pleasant fancies? What sort of gold have they sent down the river to reward us?
Dragon fire and ruin. From whom should we claim the recompense of our damage
and aid for our widows and orphans?
As you see, the master had not got his position for nothing. The result of his
words was that for the moment the people quite forgot their idea of a new king,
and turned their angry thoughts towards Thoren and his company. Wild and bitter
words were shouted from many sides, and some of those who had before sung the
old songs loudest were now heard as loudly crying that the dwarves had
stirred the dragon up against them deliberately.
"Fools," said Bard, why waste words and wrath on those unhappy creatures?
Doubtless they perished first in fire before Smout came to us. Then, even as
he was speaking, the thought came into his heart of the fabled treasure of the
mountain lying without guard or owner, and he fell suddenly silent. He thought
of the master's words and of Dale rebuilt and filled with golden bells, if
he could but find the men. At length he spoke again, "This is no time for angry
words, master, or for considering weighty plans of change. There is work
to do. I serve you still, though after a while I may think again of your words,
and go north with any that will follow me." Then he stroed off to help in the
ordering of the camps, and in the care of the sick and the wounded. But the
master scowlled at his back as he went, and remained sitting on the ground. He
thought much, but said little, unless it was to call loudly for men to bring him
fire and food. Now everywhere Bard went, he found talk running like fire among
the people, concerning the vast treasure that was now unguarded. Men spoke of the
recompense for all their harm that they would soon get from it, and wealth over
and to spare with which to buy rich things from the south, and it cheered
them greatly in their plight. That was as well, for the night was bitter and
miserable. Shelters could be contrived for few, the master had one, and there
was little food. Even the master went short. Many took ill of wet and cold and
sorrow that night and afterwards died who had escaped uninjured from the ruin
of the town. And in the days that followed there was much sickness and
great hunger. Meanwhile Bard took the lead and ordered things as he wished,
though always in the master's name, and he had a hard task to govern the people
and direct the preparations for their protection and housing. Probably most of
them would have perished in the winter that now hurried after autumn if help
had not been to hand. But help came swiftly, for borrowed at once had speedy
messengers sent up the river to the forest to ask the aid of the king of the
elves of the wood, and these messengers had found a host already on the move,
although it was then only the third day after the fall of Smog. The Alburn King
had received news from his own messengers and from the birds that loved
his folk, and already knew much of what had happened.
Very great indeed was the commotion among all things, with wings that dwelt
on the borders of the desolation of the dragon. The air was filled with circling
flocks, and their swift flying messengers flew here and there across
the sky. Above the borders of the forest there was whistling, crying, and piping.
Far over Murkwood, tidings spread. Smal is dead. Leaves rustled and startled
ears were lifted. Even before the elven king rode forth, the news had passed
west right to the pinewoods of the Misty Mountains. Beor had heard it in his
wooden house, and the goblins were at council in their caves.
That will be the last we shall hear of Thor and Oaken Shield, I fear, said the
king. He would have done better to have remained my guest. It is an ill wind all
the same, he added, that blows no one any good, for he too had not forgotten
the legend of the wealth of Thor. So it was that Bard's messengers found him now
marching with many spearmen and bowman, and crows were gathered thick above him,
for they thought that war was awakening again, such as had not been in those
parts for a long age. But the king, when he received the prayers of Bard, had
pity, for he was the lord of a good and kindly people. So turning his march,
which had at first been direct towards the mountain, he hastened now down the
river to the long lake. He had not boats or rafts enough for his host, and they
were forced to go the slower way by foot. But great store of goods he sent
ahead by water. Still elves are lightfooted, and though they were not in
these days much used to the marches and the treacherous lands between the forest
and the lake, their going was swift.
Only 5 days after the death of the dragon, they came upon the shores and
looked on the ruins of the town. Their welcome was good, as may be expected,
and the men and their master were ready to make any bargain for the future in
return for the elven king's aid. Their plans were soon made with the women and
the children, the old and the unfit. The master remained behind, and with him
were some men of crafts and many skilled elves. And they busied themselves
felling trees and collecting the timber sent down from the forest. Then they set
about raising many huts by the shore against the oncoming winter. And also
under the master's direction, they began the planning of a new town, designed
more fair and large even than before, but not in the same place. They removed
northward higher up the shore. Forever after they had a dread of the water
where the dragon lay. He would never again return to his golden bed, but was
stretched cold as stone, twisted upon the floor of the shallows. There, for
ages his huge bones could be seen in calm weather amid the ruined piles of
the old town. But few dared to cross the cursed spot, and none dared to dive into
the shivering water or recover the precious stones that fell from his rotting carcase.
But all the men of arms who are still able and the most of the elven king's
array got ready to march north to the mountain. It was thus that in 11 days
from the ruin of the town the head of their host passed the rockets at the end
of the lake and came into the desolate